{
  "reference_number": "12235",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": "Urgency is the order of the day. There are so many financial, environmental and social benefits for setting a target now to enable long\n term business investment, diversification and maximum carbon reduction. By setting a target now, stability and certainty are enablers\n\n for everyone to make smart choices"
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": "The most ambitious targets should be set to enable maximum push and opportunity. That said, I understand Methane creates a\n complex issue nationally. However, accelerating the carbon dioxide target to being even more ambitious than 2050 (target 2040) may\n\n help other gases in the long term. The reality is though, if we do not stay as close to 1.5 degrees increase, nature may decide what\n the long term opportunities are. We have to be brave, courageous and lead as we are a small enough country to change our own\n course."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": "We should not be using international carbon units to offset our emissions. We should also not be having such a heavy reliance on\n\n forestry as that may allow us not to concentrate and innovate in other sectors and industry's with the urgency and funding forestry\n might get. Future generations need us to evolve our way of living on every aspect in order for them to even live simply."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "This target should be non-negotiable, with the only exception of natural disasters needing us to re-think our future requirements."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Short term targets/budgets will enable industry and legislation to have some level of short term goals to aim for enabling certainly and\n direction. The reporting on these should be very transparent, so everyone can see where we are winning and where we need to\n focus our efforts. The ability to manipulate the reporting must be impossible. Honesty must be the goal here. No one wins if the\n\n numbers are not true."
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "Yes - each incoming Government should have the option to review the third budget in the sequence",
      "answer_index": 14,
      "notes": "An incoming government may not be in situ by the tine the third budget becomes reality so I struggle with giving them that freedom.\nHowever, I accept these budgets may have to change in order to meet the long term goals. The Climate Commission must be able to\n\nhelp steer and guide any changes."
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "Unless under extremely exceptional circumstances - with the agreement of the wider Country so the Government does not have the\ncomplete decision making ability."
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Transparency has to be achieved all the way through to ensure everyone understands the severity, complexity and difficulty involved.\n\nAs Climate Change increases around us, more people will become more consciously aware and wanting/needing to understand what\nis being achieved. Sharing plans will engage the debate required nationally to ensure the changes needed, happen."
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Target Topics - Reducing Carbon, divesting away from all fossil fuels, reversing of mobility so car is lest favored and infrastructure can\n\nsupport low carbon movement. Housing - Enabling passive house living. Industry - Diversification into less intensive industries to\nenable growth in a smart carbon free world. Who - Industry leaders, sustainability and climate experts, climate scientists, innovate\nentrepreneurs, community leaders, global experts who have demonstrated clear climate change leadership. Targets/plans -\n\nMeaningful, relatable, high level with the ability to break down into regional targets/plans. The plans must all be science based to\nensure they are ultimately impactful and will help NZ contribute in holding Climate change at 1.5 degrees."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "The Government will need objective, expert support, steerage and advice to ensure all the right elements are being considered.\n\nCollaboration and co-design will ensure a richer outcome for all. The CCC has a very important role to ensure the Government is\nalways held to accounts for its actions and outcomes."
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Advising the Government on policy settings in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 6,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "The CCC needs international input, science, business, environmental, cultural and community expertise. All groups need\nrepresentation to ensure richer targets, plans, which in turn will make change more possible. If the Commissioners are all of the same\ndiversity their advice will not be representative of the Country and the lives in which they live. Priority needs to be given to the\n\nenvironmental and climate change experts as they must always showcase what is happening on a global scale to ensure NZ is not\nleft behind."
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "But, built up over time as impacts are better understood as to what is impactful for NZ."
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    }
  ]
}
